Yan Long

2260 Hayward Street, Ann Arbor, MI, 48105 yanlong@umich.edu https://yanlong.site/ <a href="mailto:https://yanlong.site

RESEARCH

My research is broadly in the area of **cyber-physical systems security** with a particular focus on **protecting sensing-based computation** in various forms of embedded and mobile information systems using hardware-software co-design and physics modeling. I work toward hardware-ensured information authenticity in critical infrastructures and consumer electronics, as well as innovative privacy-preserving sensing in emerging IoT, AI, and healthcare technologies.

EDUCATION

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI

Sep 2019 - Present

- · Ph.D. in Electrical and Computer Engineering
- Thesis: Modeling and Mitigating Side Channels in Optical & Embedded Sensing Systems
- Dissertation committee: Kevin Fu (chair), Mingyan Liu (co-chair), Alanson Sample, Pei Zhang, Jean-Baptiste Jeannin

Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, China

Sep 2015 - June 2019

- · B.S. in Electronic and Information Engineering
- Thesis: Sound Field-based Liveness Detection in Voice Authentication
- Advisors: Wenyuan Xu, Xiaoyu Ji

WORK EXPERIENCE

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI Lead Graduate Research Assistant, Security and Privacy Research Group	Sep 2019 - Present
Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, China Undergraduate Research Assistant, Ubiquitous System Security Lab	Sep 2017 - June 2019
UCLA , Los Angeles, CA Summer Visiting Researcher, Biomimetic Research Lab	July 2018 - Sep 2018
Thundercomm , Chongqing, China Embedded Development Intern	June 2017 - Sep 2017

AWARDS & HONORS

UMich Towner Prize for Outstanding Graduate Instructor Finalist	2023
Rackham Predoctoral Fellowship (top 6 PhD candidates of UM CS&ECE)	2023
NSF/NSPW Student Travel Grant	2022
ACM SIGMOBILE Research Highlight on GetMobile	2022
Best Poster Runner-up – SenSys COVID-19 Response Research (top 8%)	2020
Outstanding Undergraduate Thesis of Zhejiang University	2019
UCLA Cross-disciplinary Scholarship in Science and Technology	2018
Zhejiang Provincial Government Scholarship (top 3% of school)	2018
Samsung Scholarship (top 5% of school)	2018
Zhejiang University Outstanding Volunteer Service Award	2017

Last updated: November 2023

Refereed Conference & Workshop Publications

C10 EM Eye: Characterizing Electromagnetic Side-channel Eavesdropping on Embedded Cameras

Yan Long, Qinhong Jiang, Chen Yan, Tobias Alam, Xiaoyu Ji, Wenyuan Xu, Kevin Fu Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS) 2024 [historical acceptance rate = 16.2%, 18 pages]

C9 GhostType: The Limits of Using Contactless Electromagnetic Interference to Inject Phantom Keys into Analog Circuits of Keyboards

Qinhong Jiang, Yanze Ren, Yan Long, Chen Yan, Yumai Sun, Xiaoyu Ji, Kevin Fu, Wenyuan Xu *Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS)* 2024 [historical acceptance rate = 16.2%, 18 pages]

C8 Characterizing and Mitigating Touchtone Eavesdropping in Smartphone Motion Sensors Connor Bolton, Yan Long, Jun Han, Josiah Hester, Kevin Fu 26th International Symposium on Research in Attacks, Intrusions, and Defenses (RAID) 2023 [acceptance rate = 50/213 = 23.5%, 14 pages]

C7 Side Eye: Characterizing the Limits of POV Acoustic Eavesdropping from Smartphone Cameras with Rolling Shutters and Movable Lenses

Yan Long, Pirouz Naghavi, Blas Kojusner, Kevin Butler, Sara Rampazzi, Kevin Fu 44th Annual IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (IEEE S&P) 2023 [acceptance rate = 195/1147 = 17%, 18 pages]

C6 Private Eye: On the Limits of Textual Screen Peeking via Eyeglass Reflections in Video Conferencing

Yan Long, Chen Yan, Shilin Xiao, Shivan Prasad, Wenyuan Xu, Kevin Fu 44th Annual IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (IEEE S&P) 2023 [acceptance rate = 195/1147 = 17%, 18 pages]

C5 Position Paper: Space System Threat Models Must Account for Satellite Sensor Spoofing

Benjamin Cyr, Yan Long, Takeshi Sugawara, Kevin Fu Workshop on Security of Space and Satellite Systems (**SpaceSec**) 2023 [acceptance rate = 10/19 = 52.6%, 6 pages]

C4 Side Auth: Sensor Side Channels Considered Beneficial by Synthesizing Virtual Sensors for Authentication

Yan Long, Kevin Fu

ACM/ACSA New Security Paradigms Workshop (NSPW) 2022
[acceptance rate = 38%, 8 pages]

C3 VeriMask: Facilitating Decontamination of N95 Masks in the COVID-19 Pandemic: Challenges, Lessons Learned, and Safeguarding the Future

Yan Long, Alexander Curtiss, Sara Rampazzi, Josiah Hester, Kevin Fu

ACM International Joint Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp) 2021
[acceptance rate = 22%, 29 pages]

C2 The Catcher in the Field: A Fieldprint based Spoofing Detection for Text-Independent Speaker Verification

Chen Yan, Yan Long, Xiaoyu Ji, Wenyuan Xu 26th ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (ACM CCS) 2019 [acceptance rate = 149/934 = 16%, 15 pages]

C1 A Novel Biomimetic Stimulator System for Neural Implant

Wang, Po-Min, Stanislav Culaclii, William Yang, Yan Long, Jonathan Massachi, Yi-Kai Lo, Wentai Liu

9th International IEEE/EMBS Conference on Neural Engineering (IEEE/EMBS NER) 2019 [4 pages]

Refereed Journal & Magazine Publications

J2 VeriMask: Sensor Platform for Decontamination of N95 Masks

Yan Long, Alexander Curtiss, Sara Rampazzi, Josiah Hester, Kevin Fu

Mobile Computing and Communications (GetMobile). June 2022, Vol. 26 Iss. 2. pp 25-28

[4 pages]

J1 Protecting COVID-19 Vaccine Transportation and Storage from Analog Cybersecurity Threats

Yan Long, Sara Rampazzi, Takeshi Sugawara, Kevin Fu Biomedical Instrumentation & Technology (AAMI BI&T) 55, no. 3, Oct 2021 [6 pages]

Posters & Demos

P2 Limiting the Optical-Electromagnetic Side Channel Leakage of Smartphone Cameras
Yan Long, Kevin Fu
NSF CHEST Meeting 2023

P1 Automating Decontamination of N95 Masks for Frontline Workers in COVID-19 Pandemic Yan Long, Alexander Curtiss, Sara Rampazzi, Josiah Hester, Kevin Fu

18th ACM Conference on Embedded Networked Sensor Systems (SenSys) 2020

[Best Poster Award Runner Up – COVID-19 Response Research (Top 8%)]

Submissions in Review

S1 SampleGuard: Enabling Lightweight Runtime Monitoring and Characterization of Android Zero-permission Sensor Usage from User Space

Yan Long, Tobias Alam, Kevin Fu Undergoing revision at 24th Privacy Enhancing Technologies Symposium (**PETS**) 2024 [14 pages]

TALKS

Security of Computer Systems with Non-Computational Sensor Side Channels

MIT CSAIL Security Seminar, Oct 4, 2023

Host: Mengjia Yan

Protecting Health Care and Cyberphysical Systems

University of Washington CSE Security Seminar (joint talk with Dr. Kevin Fu), Oct 11, 2023

Host: Franziska Roesner and Joshua Smith

Acoustic Eavesdropping Using A Smartphone Camera

Yan Long et al.

US Patent, application filed, 2023

A Method for Detecting Voice Replay Attacks

Xioayu Ji, Yan Long, Wenyuan Xu, Chen Yan China Invention Patent. ZL 2019 1 0303649.3

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

EECS 498/598 Embedded Security (~10 undergrad and ~25 graduate students)	Fall 2022
EECS 505 Computational DS & ML (~250 graduate students)	Fall 2021
EECS 298 Applied Comp. ML for Sci. & Eng. (~150 undergrad students)	Fall 2021
EECS 501 Probability & Random Process (~80 graduate students)	Winter 2021

SERVICE

Professional Activities

Technical program committee member:

- ISOC Symposium on Vehicle Security and Privacy (VehicleSec) 2024, Poster/Demo Session
- International Conference on Mobility, Sensing and Networking (IEEE MSN) 2023
- International Workshop on Security and Privacy of Sensing Systems (Sensors S&P) 2023
- Annual Embedded Security Workshop (EmSec) 2020

Reviewer:

- IEEE Transactions on Dependable and Secure Computing (TDSC)
- IEEE Internet of Things Journal (IoTJ)
- IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications (TWC)
- ACM Transactions on Privacy and Security (TOPS)
- ACM Proceedings on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Tech (IMWUT)

Sub-reviewer:

- IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics (TIE)
- IEEE Security & Privacy Journal
- ACM Conference On Mobile Computing And Networking (MobiCom) 2023
- USENIX Security Symposium 2020
- Network and Distributed System Security (NDSS) Symposium 2020
- ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS) 2019

Student Advising

Sarah Bargfrede	B.S. Computer Science	2023-Present
Jiaming Yao	M.S. Data Science	2023-Present
Emiko Sano	High-school student	2023-Present
Tobias Alam	B.S. Computer Science (papers at NDSS'24 and PETS'24)	2022-Present
Yumai Sun	M.S. Electrical and Computer Engineering (paper at NDSS'24)	2022-2023
Haoliang Cheng	B.S. Computer Engineering (now: ECE master's at CMU)	2022-2023
Shivan Prasad	B.S. Computer Science (paper at IEEE SP'23)	2021-2022
Mia Li	B.S. Computer Science (now: Salesforce)	2020
Weikun Lyu	B.S. Computer Science (now: Meta)	2020